hey everyone welcome again to end the
lesson in the stores car automation
course
today I am going to talk about
conditional Loops a loop such as a if
else condition where and how you can use
that in Tosca
so we'll see a scenario I have picked up
a very simple flow where it will just
open the application log in the user it
will add the product and then it will
close the application this is the same
application the swag labs and we have
already seen this flow right so it will
just go here and it will click on this
add to cart for this first product and
it will add the product into the cart
now what I have done purposefully is I
have already done that manually right so
the product is already in the cart and
what that has done is it has changed
this particular
button to remove instead of add to cart
now what is going to happen is it is
going uh to fail this particular test
case because Tosca is not able to find
this particular button right but
in some scenarios you might want to fail
this particular scenario but in some
cases you also want to just go ahead and
execute your test cases even though that
button is not present right so your test
should be dynamically able to
come out of these scenarios right you
don't always want to fail your scenarios
you want to recover from these type of
cases and you want to handle that
logically uh within your status cases
right so for in these type of scenarios
we can use conditional Loops right so we
can check whether a particular element
is present before actually performing
that action on on that particular
element this is a very common scenario
whenever you are developing any task
automation test cases you have to take
care of this Dynamic early changing
elements right in your application
so what we'll do is uh let's first go
ahead and execute this particular
scenario so that we can see that it is
going to fail and then we are going to
put the logic in terms of how we can put
the if else condition in this particular
test case okay
so let me first run this particular test
case
and now as you can see Tosca is not able
to find that particular button and it is
ultimately going to fail this test case
okay so we'll see uh why it has failed
in the Tosca
report so we'll see here we'll go to add
product and as you can see Tosca is
complaining about could not find
add to cart with the following
properties which is completely valid
right so that button is not present and
that's why the test case is failing
but what if I don't want to fail this
test case right I want to check whether
this button is present or not before
actually performing that operation right
so in this kind of scenarios we have to
use some conditional Loops okay
so let's go ahead and come to this test
case and here you will find there are
options for conditional Loops right so
when I right click you will see there is
a create a statement and if I click on
this it's going to create a if else step
okay so if condition and then a then
condition okay so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to drag and drop it after
login user okay and in this add product
right so this particular step I am going
to put it inside my condition okay so
this is
this is the place where you uh specify
what condition you want to check okay
uh based on this particular condition
whether it passes or fails then it is
going to perform the step which you
mentioned in the then part okay
so here uh
what I want to do is I don't want to
click on this okay I'm going to change
the action mode to verify so instead of
input it will be verify okay
and instead of Click what I'm going to
do is I'm going to put a condition here
enabled equals to true
okay
so if this button is enabled then only
this condition will be satisfied
and once this condition is satisfied
what I'm going to do is I'm going to go
ahead and then
I want to add the step
to click on this button okay
so let's go to add to cart and here I'm
going to now click on this button the
same thing which we are doing earlier
but now the difference is we are not
directly going and clicking on that
button we are putting some logic so that
it can be checked whether it is present
or not depending on some scenario and
then we are going to perform some
operation okay
so this is how you can add if else
statement in your test steps in a tasker
test case and then you can add your
steps uh so you can put a condition and
then you can add what you want to do if
that condition is met or not met okay
now what this will do is it will tell
Tosca that go ahead and check the
condition first and then perform the
operation so this way my test case would
not fail in this particular tester so
let's go ahead and check whether this is
working or not so I'm going to run this
in scratchbook
and it's going through the same flow but
uh with some logic behind it okay so
let's see whether Tosca is able to now
handle this particular scenario or not
so initially it will try to find that
button but since we have put a FL
statement it's going to go through some
checks okay so it's going to enter this
if condition now okay and then it is
going to go into condition
and we have mentioned that it should
check for this button to be enabled now
as you can see it is saying could not
find button so this condition is not
satisfied and that is why there is a
cross mark on this condition and the
test step okay so what basically has
happened is now since the condition is
not met it is not going to execute the
then part okay so that way uh the test
case has not failed it has passed okay
now if my application scenario changes
right if the add to cart button uh
reappears what will happen it will go
through the flow okay so let's see that
part as well so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to go to my website
and I'm going to either remove it or
also I can reset the App State so it
will reset everything okay
and then I'm going to close this okay
now let's try and run this again and
this time you will see
uh it will also execute the then part
okay
so let's see it is going to click on add
to cart
okay and the test case will pass
so let's go and see
the If part right now okay so let me
expand this
and now uh in the condition part you
will see that the add to cart
verification was successful and that's
why there is a tick mark here and in the
then part it is going to execute
whatever step we have added here okay so
both the condition and the then part
will be executed
so as you can see uh this gives you more
flexibility in terms of how you want to
handle uh particular scenarios in your
application
and using this if else condition you can
handle uh some Dynamic elements in your
application or some Dynamic scenarios
so stay tuned
um And subscribe to our Channel more
Tosca videos are coming up we'll try to
upload a new Tosca video every Friday so
look out for these videos uh log into
our Channel every Friday and learn
something more about this amazing
automation tool called Tosca